<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2002-2004 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors,
  as applicable.

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Apache FTP Server :: Overview</title>
        <author email="rana_b@yahoo.com">Rana Bhattacharyya</author>
    </properties>

    <head>
        <link rel="shortcut icon" href="favicon.ico" />
        <link rel="icon" href="favicon.ico" />
    </head>

    <body>
        <section name="Overview">
            <p>The Apache FTP Server is a 100% pure Java FTP server. We have designed
              it to be a complete and portable ftp server engine solution based on
              currently available open protocols.
            </p>
            <p>It is also a FTP application platform. We have developed a Java API
               to let you write Java code to process FTP event notifications that
               we call the Ftplet API. Apache FTP Server provides an implementation
               of FTP server to support this API.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Features">
            <ol>
                <li>100% pure Java, free, open source resumable FTP server!!!</li>
                <li>Multi platform support and multithreaded design.</li>
                <li>User virtual directory, write permission, idle time-out and upload/download bandwidth limitation support.</li>
                <li>You can monitor all the user activities.</li>
                <li>Anonymous login support.</li>
                <li>Both upload and download files are resumable.</li>
                <li>Handles both ASCII and binary data transfers.</li>
                <li>IP restriction support to allow/ban IPs.</li>
                <li>Database and LDAP can be used to store user data.</li>
                <li>All the FTP messages are customizable.</li>
                <li>Implicit/explicit SSL/TLS support.</li>
                <li>MDTM support - your users can change the date-time stamp of files.</li>
                <li>"MODE Z" support for faster data upload/download.</li>
                <li>Custom user manager, IP restrictor, logger can be added easily.</li>
                <li>User event notifications can be added (Ftplet).</li>
            </ol>
        </section>
        <section name="Disclaimers">
            <p>Ftpserver is an effort undergoing incubation at the 
               Apache Software Foundation (ASF), sponsored by the Incubator PMC. 
               Incubation is required of all newly accepted projects until a further 
               review indicates that the infrastructure, communications, and decision
               making process have stabilized in a manner consistent with other 
               successful ASF projects. While incubation status is not necessarily a 
               reflection of the completeness or stability of the code, it does 
               indicate that the project has yet to be fully endorsed by the ASF.
            </p>
        </section>    
    </body>
</document>